{"tossups": [{"question": "As an ethos emphasizing content rather than form for artists working with this material, Harvey Littleton coined the slogan \"technique is cheap\". The colorful, spiraling public sculpture The Sun was made using this medium by an eyepatch-wearing artist. St. Matthew's Church in Jersey is extensively decorated with artworks made of this material, created by a man who made hood ornaments like Spirit of the Wind. The usage of this material in sculptures was promoted by the members of the \"studio\" movement, such as Dale Chihuly (chih-HOO-lee). A form of this material called \"favrile\" was trademarked by an American Art Nouveau contemporary of Rene\u0301 Lalique who made many lamps. For 10 points, name this artistic material blown by Louis Comfort Tiffany.", "answer": "studio glass [or specific types of glass, such as stained glass]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "As an ethos emphasizing content rather than form for artists working with this material, Harvey Littleton coined the slogan \"technique is cheap\". The colorful, spiraling public sculpture The Sun was made using this medium by an eyepatch-wearing artist. St. Matthew's Church in Jersey is extensively decorated with artworks made of this material, created by a man who made hood ornaments like Spirit of the Wind. The usage of this material in sculptures was promoted by the members of the \"studio\" movement, such as Dale Chihuly (chih-HOO-lee). A form of this material called \"favrile\" was trademarked by an American Art Nouveau contemporary of Rene\u0301 Lalique who made many lamps. For 10 points, name this artistic material blown by Louis Comfort Tiffany.", "answer": "studio glass [or specific types of glass, such as stained glass]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A poem set at this place uses the recurring image of a man \"who looked so wistfully at the day\". A man living here wrote that Christ \"ranks with the poets\" and that he doesn't \"regret for a single moment having lived for pleasure\". A poem set at this place was inspired by the death of Charles Thomas Wooldridge, a former member of the Royal Horse Guards. A poem set here notes that \"some do it with a bitter look, some with a flattering word\", while cowards use a kiss. While residing at this place, a man wrote a spiritually themed letter addressed to \"Bosie\", the son of the Marquess of Queensbury. A poem set at this place notes that \"each man kills the thing he loves\". For 10 points, name this place where De Profundis was written, the prison that Oscar Wilde wrote a \"ballad\" about.", "answer": "Reading Gaol (RED-ing JAIL) [or HM Prison Reading]", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A poem set at this place uses the recurring image of a man \"who looked so wistfully at the day\". A man living here wrote that Christ \"ranks with the poets\" and that he doesn't \"regret for a single moment having lived for pleasure\". A poem set at this place was inspired by the death of Charles Thomas Wooldridge, a former member of the Royal Horse Guards. A poem set here notes that \"some do it with a bitter look, some with a flattering word\", while cowards use a kiss. While residing at this place, a man wrote a spiritually themed letter addressed to \"Bosie\", the son of the Marquess of Queensbury. A poem set at this place notes that \"each man kills the thing he loves\". For 10 points, name this place where De Profundis was written, the prison that Oscar Wilde wrote a \"ballad\" about.", "answer": "Reading Gaol (RED-ing JAIL) [or HM Prison Reading]", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Zweigenhaft and Domhoff wrote about how the presence of women and minorities in this group has failed to change its values in a book about \"Diversity\" in this group. Robert Dahl argued against the existence of this group in a book examining \"dispersed inequalities\" in New Haven politics. This group enforces its \"crackpot definitions upon world reality\" according to a chapter on the \"Higher Immorality\". The \"Metropolitan 400\" and the \"Warlords\" are parts of this group, according to a book that places it at the top of a pyramid above \"the middle level\" and the \"masses\". That book titled for this group argues that it is made up of the overlapping factions of political, business, and military leaders. For 10 points, name this group that governs America, according to a 1957 book by C. Wright Mills.", "answer": "the power elite [prompt on the elite]", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "Zweigenhaft and Domhoff wrote about how the presence of women and minorities in this group has failed to change its values in a book about \"Diversity\" in this group. Robert Dahl argued against the existence of this group in a book examining \"dispersed inequalities\" in New Haven politics. This group enforces its \"crackpot definitions upon world reality\" according to a chapter on the \"Higher Immorality\". The \"Metropolitan 400\" and the \"Warlords\" are parts of this group, according to a book that places it at the top of a pyramid above \"the middle level\" and the \"masses\". That book titled for this group argues that it is made up of the overlapping factions of political, business, and military leaders. For 10 points, name this group that governs America, according to a 1957 book by C. Wright Mills.", "answer": "the power elite [prompt on the elite]", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "In the columns of Jack Anderson, this man was dubbed an \"anti-poverty czar\" and was alleged to spend thousands to redecorate his office. Milton Friedman claimed that Ronald Reagan's biggest mistake was not choosing this man for his Vice President. When describing people looting vases from a museum, this man noted \"stuff happens\" and that \"freedom's untidy\". When answering a reporter's question, he mused \"there are known knowns\". During the Halloween Massacre, this man went from being Chief of Staff to holding a Cabinet level post. Under the Ford presidency, he became the youngest man to hold his Cabinet position, a post he returned to in the 2000s and later resigned after the Abu Ghraib prisoner abuse scandal. For 10 points, name this man, George W. Bush's first Secretary of Defense.", "answer": "Donald Henry Rumsfeld ", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Endo- and exocytosis can be analyzed using the ratiometric and superecliptic pH-sensitive types of this protein called pHluorin (FLOOR-in). A biosensor for the glutathione redox potential and thus ROS production is the \"Mito-Ro\" mutant of this protein. Some mutants of this protein can't be deprotonated at a specific site because the HBI tripeptide that is normally ionized after cyclization has its phenol replaced with an indole. That mutation in this protein has a substitution for tryptophan at tyrosine-66. This protein was discovered at Friday Harbor labs by Shimomura Osamu, who shared a Nobel Prize with Chalfie and Tsien for their research on this beta-barrel protein. For 10 points, name this fluorophore with a major emission peak at 509 nanometers derived from the bioluminescent Aequorea jellyfish.", "answer": "GFP [or green fluorescent protein]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Endo- and exocytosis can be analyzed using the ratiometric and superecliptic pH-sensitive types of this protein called pHluorin (FLOOR-in). A biosensor for the glutathione redox potential and thus ROS production is the \"Mito-Ro\" mutant of this protein. Some mutants of this protein can't be deprotonated at a specific site because the HBI tripeptide that is normally ionized after cyclization has its phenol replaced with an indole. That mutation in this protein has a substitution for tryptophan at tyrosine-66. This protein was discovered at Friday Harbor labs by Shimomura Osamu, who shared a Nobel Prize with Chalfie and Tsien for their research on this beta-barrel protein. For 10 points, name this fluorophore with a major emission peak at 509 nanometers derived from the bioluminescent Aequorea jellyfish.", "answer": "GFP [or green fluorescent protein]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Saint Pachomius the Great supposedly introduced the Eastern Orthodox equivalent of these objects to replace tossing pebbles into bowls, and Saint Anthony the Great standardized the use of seven crosses per knot to prevent demonic interference. These objects are called mala in Sanskrit, and are known by this name in some Buddhist, Sikh, and Hindu traditions. Though rejected by the Ahmadiyya, these objects are known as misbaha in Islam and used to practice tasbih; they likely were imported into Catholicism by crusaders encountering misbaha. Baha\u0301'i\u0301 employ these objects in their daily repetition of the Alla\u0301h-u-Abha\u0301, and Catholics use them to track repetitions of the Lord's Prayer, Hail Mary, and other prayers. For 10 points, give this type of ritual object used to keep track of devotional repetitions, including the Rosary.", "answer": "prayer beads [or prayer rope until \"mala\" is read; do not accept \"rosary\"]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "Saint Pachomius the Great supposedly introduced the Eastern Orthodox equivalent of these objects to replace tossing pebbles into bowls, and Saint Anthony the Great standardized the use of seven crosses per knot to prevent demonic interference. These objects are called mala in Sanskrit, and are known by this name in some Buddhist, Sikh, and Hindu traditions. Though rejected by the Ahmadiyya, these objects are known as misbaha in Islam and used to practice tasbih; they likely were imported into Catholicism by crusaders encountering misbaha. Baha\u0301'i\u0301 employ these objects in their daily repetition of the Alla\u0301h-u-Abha\u0301, and Catholics use them to track repetitions of the Lord's Prayer, Hail Mary, and other prayers. For 10 points, give this type of ritual object used to keep track of devotional repetitions, including the Rosary.", "answer": "prayer beads [or prayer rope until \"mala\" is read; do not accept \"rosary\"]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "It's not concentration, but the gradient of this quantity is set to zero to calculate the self-diffusion coefficient. For a gas, this quantity is equal to its standard state variety plus quantity R T times fugacity. According to one approximation, this quantity equals the Fermi energy plus the potential energy for a cloud of trapped fermions. Noting that this quantity is equal in all phases allows one to derive the Gibbs phase rule. This quantity is related to pressure and temperature in the Gibbs\u00c2\u2013Duhem equation. For a component in a solution, this quantity is defined as the partial derivative of internal energy with respect to the component. For 10 points, name this energy that can be absorbed or released during a chemical reaction, often symbolized mu.", "answer": "chemical potential [or mu until it is read and prompt afterwards]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In a story by this author, a man goes to simply clean out his drawers, but becomes depressed reading about his old letters and ends up shooting himself. In another story by this man, the protagonist first meets the title thing after waving to a Brazilian boat. That story by this author ends with a man burning down his house to kill the title supernatural creature, but concludes \"He is not dead... I suppose I must kill myself\". In another of his stories, a church bell is rung over and over by a woman after she uses a dessert knife to stab the title character after he makes a speech mocking France. In that story by this author, the prostitute Rachel kills an effeminate German captain during the Franco-Prussian War. For 10 points, name this French author of \"The Horla\", \"Mademoiselle Fifi\", and \"The Necklace\".", "answer": "Guy de Maupassant [or Henri Rene Albert Guy de Maupassant]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Through a deal with Sir Dudley Carleton, this artist amassed the largest collection of antique sculpture in Europe. The French Academy was torn between a faction backing this man's view that color was more essential than drawing, and the Poussinistes (poo-san-EASTS), who argued the opposite. He subcontracted still-lifes in his large paintings to artists like Jacob Jordaens. The bloody siege of this artist's home city inspired his painting in which a brutish man prepares to slam dunk a baby under the orders of Herod the Great. In 1609, this artist of The Massacre of the Innocents returned from Italy to Antwerp, where he painted a triptych showing The Raising of the Cross. For 10 points, name this Flemish Baroque painter fond of painting fleshy nude women.", "answer": "Sir Peter Paul Rubens", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This event involved a payment of nearly four hundred thousand pounds known as \"The Equivalent\". A political group called the Squadrone Volante ensured that this event occurred. The \"twelve limitations\" meant to reduce the effects of this event were proposed by Andrew Fletcher. This event was partially motivated by the opportunity to recover from the failure to establish a colony in Panama's Darien region. This event was symbolized by a rose and thistle growing from the same stem. After this event during the reign of Queen Anne, the song \"Why Should I Be So Sad On My Wedding Day?\" was played by the bells of St. Giles' Cathedral in Edinburgh. For 10 points, identify this 1707 union of two countries that officially formed the Kingdom of Great Britain.", "answer": "the union of England and Scotland [or the 1707 Act of Union; or obvious equivalents of \"union\"; or the formation of the UK or obvious equivalents until \"formed\" is read]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This event involved a payment of nearly four hundred thousand pounds known as \"The Equivalent\". A political group called the Squadrone Volante ensured that this event occurred. The \"twelve limitations\" meant to reduce the effects of this event were proposed by Andrew Fletcher. This event was partially motivated by the opportunity to recover from the failure to establish a colony in Panama's Darien region. This event was symbolized by a rose and thistle growing from the same stem. After this event during the reign of Queen Anne, the song \"Why Should I Be So Sad On My Wedding Day?\" was played by the bells of St. Giles' Cathedral in Edinburgh. For 10 points, identify this 1707 union of two countries that officially formed the Kingdom of Great Britain.", "answer": "the union of England and Scotland [or the 1707 Act of Union; or obvious equivalents of \"union\"; or the formation of the UK or obvious equivalents until \"formed\" is read]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A god who acts rudely at one of these events is later given fourteen demons by Enki and disguised as an old man in order to withstand his forthcoming punishment. After failing to bow to Namtar at one of these events, Nergal is sent to the underworld, where he spends seven days sleeping with Ereshkigal. Inanna organizes one of these events in order to inebriate Enki and steal his me. Thor makes four consecutive threats to kill Loki towards the end of one of these events featuring the lengthiest Norse flyting. The Lokasenna takes place during one of these events hosted by Aegir. Demeter eats the shoulder of Pelops at, for 10 points, what type of large celebratory meal?", "answer": "feast [or banquet; or dinner; or meal before \"meal\" is read; or obvious equivalents]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "A god who acts rudely at one of these events is later given fourteen demons by Enki and disguised as an old man in order to withstand his forthcoming punishment. After failing to bow to Namtar at one of these events, Nergal is sent to the underworld, where he spends seven days sleeping with Ereshkigal. Inanna organizes one of these events in order to inebriate Enki and steal his me. Thor makes four consecutive threats to kill Loki towards the end of one of these events featuring the lengthiest Norse flyting. The Lokasenna takes place during one of these events hosted by Aegir. Demeter eats the shoulder of Pelops at, for 10 points, what type of large celebratory meal?", "answer": "feast [or banquet; or dinner; or meal before \"meal\" is read; or obvious equivalents]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "A catalyst for this event was when two men at Sycae were spared death when the scaffolds for their hanging broke, and they fled into a church. After not being able to find Probus during this event, a crowd burned his house. During it, a woman noted \"royal purple is the noblest shroud\" in refusing to leave; that woman also insisted on the execution of Anastasius' nephew in its aftermath. Participants in this event wanted to crown Hypatius, but were outmaneuvered by the eunuch Narses and slaughtered by Mundus. People in this event demanded the removal of the men who drafted the Corpus Juris Civilis. The initial participants in its violence were \"Blues\" and \"Greens\", fans of chariot races at the Hippodrome. For 10 points, what 532 riots targeted Justinian I in Constantinople?", "answer": "Nika riots ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This kind of symbol is used to denote morphisms that are treated as their own objects, the slice category. Though it is not a pipe or dagger, the Sheffer stroke is sometimes denoted using a form of this symbol named for Charles Sanders Peirce; that symbol is sometimes called the \"Quine dagger\" and is used to represent the NAND operation. In another notation that uses these symbols, removing them creates power towers, allowing for the hyperoperation of exponentials. These symbols are used to express incredibly large numbers in a notation developed by Donald Knuth. To convey the meaning of \"iff\", spelled \"I-F-F\", a double-headed one of these symbols is used. For 10 points, name this symbol used to signify conditionals, such as p implies q.", "answer": "arrows [or up arrows]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This kind of symbol is used to denote morphisms that are treated as their own objects, the slice category. Though it is not a pipe or dagger, the Sheffer stroke is sometimes denoted using a form of this symbol named for Charles Sanders Peirce; that symbol is sometimes called the \"Quine dagger\" and is used to represent the NAND operation. In another notation that uses these symbols, removing them creates power towers, allowing for the hyperoperation of exponentials. These symbols are used to express incredibly large numbers in a notation developed by Donald Knuth. To convey the meaning of \"iff\", spelled \"I-F-F\", a double-headed one of these symbols is used. For 10 points, name this symbol used to signify conditionals, such as p implies q.", "answer": "arrows [or up arrows]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A character in this novel is an abolitionist who joins the Confederate Army but vows not to kill anyone because he feels guilty over the suicide of his friend Duncan. That character in this novel is obsessed with finding the slave Phebe, who discovered his affair with Annabelle Trice. The narrator of this novel adopts a nihilist, random view of life after giving an old man with a facial twitch a ride back east. Its narrator researches his ancestor, Cass Mastern, but eventually gives up and enters what he calls the Great Sleep. Near the end of this novel, Dr. Adam Stanton shoots a man to death at the Capitol building. It is narrated by reporter Jack Burden, who is the aide to the Huey Long-inspired politician Willie Stark. For 10 points, name this novel by Robert Penn Warren.", "answer": "All the King's Men", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A character in this novel is an abolitionist who joins the Confederate Army but vows not to kill anyone because he feels guilty over the suicide of his friend Duncan. That character in this novel is obsessed with finding the slave Phebe, who discovered his affair with Annabelle Trice. The narrator of this novel adopts a nihilist, random view of life after giving an old man with a facial twitch a ride back east. Its narrator researches his ancestor, Cass Mastern, but eventually gives up and enters what he calls the Great Sleep. Near the end of this novel, Dr. Adam Stanton shoots a man to death at the Capitol building. It is narrated by reporter Jack Burden, who is the aide to the Huey Long-inspired politician Willie Stark. For 10 points, name this novel by Robert Penn Warren.", "answer": "All the King's Men", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The founder of this group insisted that his sons-in-law, Frederick and Arthur, add his last name to their names. It was opposed by its founder's son, Ballington, who formed a similar, rival group, and by groups of people called the Skeletons, who believed in the three B's of \"Beef\", \"Beer\", and \"Bacca\". This organization got its name after another of its founder's sons, Bramwell, said, \"I'm no volunteer, I'm a regular!\". It grew out of the work its founder and his wife, Catherine, did in the East End of London, where two of its three S's were \"soup and soap\". This group publishes the newspaper The War Cry and its founder was known as the \"General\". For 10 points, what Christian charitable group founded by William Booth is structured like a military?", "answer": "The Salvation Army", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The founder of this group insisted that his sons-in-law, Frederick and Arthur, add his last name to their names. It was opposed by its founder's son, Ballington, who formed a similar, rival group, and by groups of people called the Skeletons, who believed in the three B's of \"Beef\", \"Beer\", and \"Bacca\". This organization got its name after another of its founder's sons, Bramwell, said, \"I'm no volunteer, I'm a regular!\". It grew out of the work its founder and his wife, Catherine, did in the East End of London, where two of its three S's were \"soup and soap\". This group publishes the newspaper The War Cry and its founder was known as the \"General\". For 10 points, what Christian charitable group founded by William Booth is structured like a military?", "answer": "The Salvation Army", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A novel written by an author with this surname concludes with thirteen men dying in succession while trying to obtain clean water. A character created by an author with this last name contemplates the meaning of a quote about the \"madness of art\" after reading Henry James's story \"The Middle Years\". An author with this surname described a member of the Trotta family saving the emperor from a sniper at Solferino in his novel Radetzky March. A writer with this surname wrote a book in which Amy Bellette may actually be Anne Frank, The Ghost Writer. That author with this surname wrote about the \"Swede\", who is haunted by his daughter's act of terrorism, in a novel narrated by Nathan Zuckerman. For 10 points, give the surname of the author of American Pastoral and Portnoy's Complaint.", "answer": "Roth [or Joseph Roth; or Philip Roth]", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A novel written by an author with this surname concludes with thirteen men dying in succession while trying to obtain clean water. A character created by an author with this last name contemplates the meaning of a quote about the \"madness of art\" after reading Henry James's story \"The Middle Years\". An author with this surname described a member of the Trotta family saving the emperor from a sniper at Solferino in his novel Radetzky March. A writer with this surname wrote a book in which Amy Bellette may actually be Anne Frank, The Ghost Writer. That author with this surname wrote about the \"Swede\", who is haunted by his daughter's act of terrorism, in a novel narrated by Nathan Zuckerman. For 10 points, give the surname of the author of American Pastoral and Portnoy's Complaint.", "answer": "Roth [or Joseph Roth; or Philip Roth]", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This composer's Piano Concerto No. 2 begins with a long solo passage without bar lines, and ends with a third movement in tarantella rhythm. The last movement of his Symphony No. 3 is divided into a scherzo-like C minor section and a triumphant C major finale. For a Cuban violinist, this composer wrote his E major Havanaise. A harp plucks the note D twelve times to signal midnight at the start of a tone poem by this composer that calls for a solo violin with its E string lowered a half step. In the penultimate movement of a suite by this composer, two pianos accompany a solo cello melody that depicts the beautiful movement of the title \"Swan\". For 10 points, name this composer of Danse macabre and Carnival of the Animals.", "answer": "Camille Saint-Sae\u0308ns (san-SAWNS) [or Charles-Camille Saint-Sae\u0308ns]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This composer's Piano Concerto No. 2 begins with a long solo passage without bar lines, and ends with a third movement in tarantella rhythm. The last movement of his Symphony No. 3 is divided into a scherzo-like C minor section and a triumphant C major finale. For a Cuban violinist, this composer wrote his E major Havanaise. A harp plucks the note D twelve times to signal midnight at the start of a tone poem by this composer that calls for a solo violin with its E string lowered a half step. In the penultimate movement of a suite by this composer, two pianos accompany a solo cello melody that depicts the beautiful movement of the title \"Swan\". For 10 points, name this composer of Danse macabre and Carnival of the Animals.", "answer": "Camille Saint-Sae\u0308ns (san-SAWNS) [or Charles-Camille Saint-Sae\u0308ns]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A rainbow of extremophilic algae coat the man-made Fly Geyser in this state. 2000-year-old duck decoys were discovered in this state's Lovelock Cave, where guano miners unearthed mummified remains supposedly belonging to the legendary Si-Te-Cah tribe described by the Paiute. The high-def Toshiba commercial Space Chair launched an armchair into near space from a site in this state. The cui- ui is endemic to this state's tufa-rich Pyramid Lake, a remnant of the prehistoric Lahontan Lake in Washoe County and the terminus of the Truckee River. This state's Black Rock Desert is the site of the Burning Man Festival. For 10 points, name this state that shares Lake Tahoe with California.", "answer": "Nevada", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "A rainbow of extremophilic algae coat the man-made Fly Geyser in this state. 2000-year-old duck decoys were discovered in this state's Lovelock Cave, where guano miners unearthed mummified remains supposedly belonging to the legendary Si-Te-Cah tribe described by the Paiute. The high-def Toshiba commercial Space Chair launched an armchair into near space from a site in this state. The cui- ui is endemic to this state's tufa-rich Pyramid Lake, a remnant of the prehistoric Lahontan Lake in Washoe County and the terminus of the Truckee River. This state's Black Rock Desert is the site of the Burning Man Festival. For 10 points, name this state that shares Lake Tahoe with California.", "answer": "Nevada", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "This adjective appears in the name of a phenomenon coined by Alexander Kashlinsky after he observed a tendency of clusters to move toward a region of the universe in between Centaurus and Vela. Space is treated as a Chaplygin (chop-LIG-in) gas in a cosmology that posits the existence of this kind of fluid. A possibly fifth fundamental force named quintessence is a dynamic form of a phenomenon described by this adjective; more traditional theories hold that the cosmological constant is a form of that phenomenon that causes the acceleration of the expansion of the universe. Approximately 70 percent of the mass-energy of the universe is in the form of energy that is described by, for 10 points, what adjective that indicates it has yet to be directly observed?", "answer": "dark [or dark flow; or dark fluid; or dark energy]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "An employee of this man, Abacuk Pricket, was a former servant of this man's benefactor Dudley Digges and was later acquitted of murdering this person. Another employee of this man, John Colman, was killed with an arrow to the neck and may have been buried at Sandy Hook, New Jersey. Jonas Poole, an agent of the English Muscovy Company, expanded on this man's discoveries, leading to the creation of the Spitsbergen whale fishery in Norway. He was last seen being set adrift with his son, John, after a successful mutiny aboard his ship, the Discovery, prompted after a winter stranded in James Bay. This man tried to find the Northwest Passage while captaining ships like the Half Moon. For 10 points, name this English sea captain who is the namesake of a large bay in northeastern Canada.", "answer": "Henry Hudson", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "After this city fell due to a bribed sentry, more than 500 citizens were murdered in Haultepenne's Fury. A treaty signed in this city ended a conflict that featured the British Royal Navy suffering the disastrous Raid on the Medway; that conflict prompted the Samuel Pepys (PEEPS) diary entry \"I think the Devil shits Dutchmen\". That treaty signed in this city ended the Second Anglo-Dutch War in 1667. A declaration named for this city was issued in response to an offer from General George Monck and promised to pardon all who recognized Charles II as the British monarch. After taking about 10,000 casualties, Justin of Nassau was forced to surrender this city to Ambrogio Spinola. For 10 points, what Dutch city surrendered to the Spanish in 1625 after an eleven-month siege?", "answer": "Breda", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}